<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://johnlowy.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://johnlowy.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-20T00:38:28+02:00</updated><id>https://johnlowy.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">My Tech Talks</title><subtitle>Sharing my tech journey and discoveries with you, one post at a time.
</subtitle><author><name>John</name></author><entry><title type="html">Efficient Database Design</title><link href="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/efficient-database-design" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Efficient Database Design" /><published>2023-04-21T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-05-10T00:56:05+02:00</updated><id>https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/efficient-database-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/efficient-database-design"><![CDATA[<p>As a database maintainer, I’ve come to learn the importance of properly arranging fields in a database table. One of the benefits of doing so is that it can help reduce disk space usage. In this article, I’ll be sharing some insights on how this works and the benefits it can bring.</p>

<p>The way database tables are designed can greatly affect their performance and storage requirements. One common mistake is to include too many fields in a table, leading to redundancy and inefficiency. By arranging the fields in a proper manner, we can avoid these issues and ensure that the table is optimized for storage.</p>

<p>One way to do this is by grouping related fields together in a table. For example, if we have a table that contains information about customers, we can group fields such as name, address, and phone number together. This not only makes the table more organized and easier to understand, but it also reduces the amount of disk space required to store the table.</p>

<p>Another approach is to use normalization to break down the table into smaller, more efficient parts. Normalization involves dividing a large table into smaller tables, each containing only related fields. This not only reduces redundancy, but it also ensures that each field is only stored once, further reducing the amount of disk space needed.</p>

<p>Proper indexing can also play a key role in reducing disk space usage. Indexing allows us to quickly search and retrieve data from a table, but it can also take up a significant amount of disk space if not done properly. By carefully choosing which fields to index and how to index them, we can reduce the amount of disk space needed for indexing.</p>

<p>To illustrate the importance of properly arranged fields, let’s consider an example. Suppose we have a table that contains information about products, including their name, price, and description. Without proper <a href="/blog/database-schema-migration-in-backend-development">database schema</a> organization, the table may contain redundant information, such as the product name being stored in multiple fields. This can quickly add up and result in a large amount of wasted disk space.</p>

<p>However, by properly arranging the fields and using normalization, we can greatly reduce the amount of disk space needed. For example, we can create a separate table for product names and link it to the main product table using a foreign key. This way, each product name is only stored once, greatly reducing the amount of redundant information and disk space needed.</p>

<p>In addition to reducing disk space usage, properly arranged fields can also improve database performance. By reducing redundancy and improving indexing, queries can be executed more quickly and efficiently, leading to faster response times and a better overall user experience.</p>

<p>In conclusion, properly arranged fields in a database table can have a significant impact on disk space usage and database performance. By grouping related fields together, using normalization, and carefully choosing which fields to index, we can ensure that our database is optimized for storage and performance.</p>]]></content><author><name>John</name></author><category term="database" /><category term="performance" /><category term="schema" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reducing Disk Space Usage Through Proper Field Arrangement]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Database Schema Migration in Backend Development</title><link href="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/database-schema-migration-in-backend-development" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Database Schema Migration in Backend Development" /><published>2023-03-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-11T00:33:53+02:00</updated><id>https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/database-schema-migration-in-backend-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/database-schema-migration-in-backend-development"><![CDATA[<p>Database schema migration is an essential task in the development of any software application that involves a database. It involves updating the database schema to reflect changes in the software’s data model, such as the addition of new fields or tables. However, schema migration is not always a straightforward process, and developers often face challenges and obstacles along the way. In this article, I will explore some of the challenges and failures that come with database schema migration and provide examples of how to overcome them.</p>

<p>The article “<a href="https://iyas.fluidal.stream/learning-from-failure-overcoming-database-schema-migration-challenges-in-backend-development.php">Overcoming Database Schema Migration Challenges in Backend Development</a>” highlights the importance of recognizing that schema migration can be a complex and time-consuming task. It emphasizes the need for developers to anticipate potential challenges and plan accordingly. The article also recommends testing the migration process on a staging environment before deploying changes to production, as this can help identify and resolve issues before they affect users.</p>

<p>I agree with the author’s perspective that failure is a crucial part of the learning process. Schema migration is an area where developers often encounter problems, and the best way to improve is to learn from these failures. A common challenge faced during schema migration is the need to maintain data integrity while making changes to the database schema. For example, suppose a developer adds a new field to a table that already contains data. In that case, they need to ensure that the new field is correctly populated with values for all existing records. Otherwise, it could cause data inconsistencies and issues down the line.</p>

<p>One way to avoid this problem is to use a database <a href="https://iyas.fluidal.stream/learning-from-failure-overcoming-database-schema-migration-challenges-in-backend-development.php">schema migration tool</a> that provides features for data migration. For example, the Schema Guard tool, mentioned in the original article, includes a feature that allows developers to define migration scripts that automatically migrate data from the old schema to the new schema. This helps ensure that data integrity is maintained while making changes to the database schema.</p>

<p>Another common challenge faced during schema migration is dealing with the impact of changes on the application’s performance. For example, if a new table is added to the database schema, it may require additional indexes or optimizations to ensure that queries are efficient. One solution to this problem is to use performance monitoring tools such as SQL Profiler or Query Analyzer to identify and address performance issues.</p>

<p>In addition to these technical challenges, developers also need to consider the impact of schema migration on other areas of the application. For example, if the schema migration involves changes to stored procedures or views, it may impact the application’s functionality. Therefore, it is essential to test the application thoroughly after making schema changes to ensure that it still works as intended.</p>

<p>In conclusion, database schema migration is a critical task in software development, but it can be challenging and lead to failures. As developers, we need to anticipate potential challenges, plan accordingly, and test thoroughly to minimize the impact of schema migration on the application. Learning from failures is an essential part of the process, and by doing so, we can improve our skills and ensure that future schema migration tasks are successful.</p>]]></content><author><name>John</name></author><category term="database," /><category term="schema," /><category term="migration" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tackling Database Schema Migration in Backend Development]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the World of Publicly Available Databases</title><link href="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/exploring-the-world-of-publicly-available-databases" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the World of Publicly Available Databases" /><published>2023-02-17T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-10T00:31:08+02:00</updated><id>https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/exploring-the-world-of-publicly-available-databases</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/exploring-the-world-of-publicly-available-databases"><![CDATA[<p>The internet is a vast repository of information, and it’s amazing how much of it is freely available to anyone who knows where to look. The internet archive is a goldmine of historical data, preserving everything from old websites to vintage software. Publicly available databases are another valuable resource, providing easy access to structured data on a wide range of topics. In this blog post, I’ll explore the world of internet archives and publicly available databases, and I’ll also introduce you to <a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/">TagTuner</a> music tagging software that hosts the historical freedb copy I used in my <a href="/blog/dusting-off-my-cd-collection">previous post</a>.</p>

<p>The internet archive, also known as the <a href="https://archive.org/web/">Wayback Machine</a>, is an amazing resource for anyone interested in history or culture. It contains a vast collection of websites, many of which have long since disappeared from the web. With the Wayback Machine, you can browse old versions of popular websites like Yahoo!, Google, and Amazon, as well as smaller, lesser-known sites that would otherwise be lost to history.</p>

<p>But the internet archive isn’t just about websites. It also contains a wealth of other digital media, including books, music, and movies. You can find rare recordings of live performances, old radio broadcasts, and even vintage commercials. And because the internet archive is a non-profit organization, it’s all available to the public for free.</p>

<p>Publicly available databases are another great resource for researchers, journalists, and anyone else looking for structured data on a particular topic. These databases cover everything from government statistics to business directories, and they’re often maintained by public institutions or non-profit organizations.</p>

<p>One of the challenges of using publicly available databases is that they can be difficult to navigate, especially if you’re not familiar with the particular dataset you’re working with. That’s where tools like TagTuner.com’s historical freedb copy can be extremely helpful. This database contains information on millions of music albums, including track listings, release dates, and artist information. With the software tools, you can easily search this massive dataset and find the information you need.</p>

<p>Of course, there are some challenges to working with internet archives and publicly available databases. For one thing, not all data is created equal. Some datasets may be incomplete or contain errors, while others may be biased in some way. It’s important to be aware of these issues and to approach any data with a critical eye.</p>

<p>Another challenge is simply the sheer volume of data that’s available. With so much information out there, it can be difficult to know where to start or how to narrow your search. This is where tools like search engines, filters, and other data management tools can be helpful.</p>

<p>Despite these challenges, however, the benefits of internet archives and publicly available databases are clear. They provide access to a wealth of information that might otherwise be lost, and they allow anyone with an internet connection to explore the world’s knowledge in a meaningful way. Whether you’re a student, a researcher, or simply someone with a curious mind, these resources are worth exploring.</p>

<p>In conclusion, the internet archive and publicly available databases are incredible resources for anyone interested in exploring the world’s knowledge. And with tools like TagTuner.com’s historical freedb copy, it’s easier than ever to navigate these massive datasets and find the information you need. So why not take some time to explore these resources for yourself? You never know what you might discover.</p>]]></content><author><name>John</name></author><category term="data" /><category term="archive" /><category term="music" /><category term="database" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How Internet Archives Revolutionized Access to Historical Information]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dusting Off My CD Collection</title><link href="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/dusting-off-my-cd-collection" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dusting Off My CD Collection" /><published>2023-01-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2023-05-10T00:13:20+02:00</updated><id>https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/dusting-off-my-cd-collection</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://johnlowy.github.io/blog/dusting-off-my-cd-collection"><![CDATA[<p>As a lover of music, I am always on the lookout for rare albums that are not readily available in digital format. Recently, while cleaning up a storage room, I stumbled upon a treasure trove of 10 rare old CDs. These albums were from different artists and genres, and I couldn’t wait to convert them into MP3s to add them to my collection.</p>

<p>The first album was from the British band Oasis, and it was their debut album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Oasis/Definitely-Maybe/album-v2fc632">Definitely Maybe</a>.” The CD box was in excellent condition, and the printed materials were intact, including the lyrics sheet. The music was pure Britpop, and the songs like “Live Forever” and “Supersonic” still hold up today.</p>

<p>The second album was from the legendary Nirvana, and it was their third and final studio album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Nirvana/In-Utero/album-v2106725">In Utero</a>.” The CD box was slightly damaged, but the printed materials were still in good condition. The songs like “Heart-Shaped Box” and “All Apologies” were a reminder of the band’s impact on music in the early 90s.</p>

<p>The third album was from the American rock band Superunknow, and it was their breakthrough album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Superunknown/Radiance/album-v214cf98">Radiance</a>.” The CD box was in excellent condition, and the printed materials were in great shape. The album had songs like “Black Hole Sun” and “Spoonman,” which were staples on alternative rock radio stations at the time.</p>

<p>The fourth album was from the American hip-hop artist Jay-Z, and it was his fourth studio album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Jay_Z/%28Volume-3%29-Life-And-Times-Of-S.-Carter/album-v2111b49">Vol. 3… Life and Times of S. Carter</a>.” The CD box was slightly damaged, but the printed materials were still in good shape. The album had hits like “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Jay_Z/Big-Pimpin%27/album-v2aa48b">Big Pimpin</a>” and “Do It Again (Put Ya Hands Up),” which showcased Jay-Z’s skills as a rapper and a businessman.</p>

<p>The fifth album was from the American rock band Pearl Jam, and it was their third studio album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Pearl-Jam/Vitalogy/album-v211cc10">Vitalogy</a>.” The CD box was in great condition, and the printed materials were in good shape. The album had songs like “Better Man” and “Corduroy,” which were a testament to the band’s longevity and influence in the rock world.</p>

<p>The sixth album was from the American alternative rock band The Smashing Pumpkins, and it was their second studio album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Smashing-Pumpkins/Siamese-Dream/album-v212de9d">Siamese Dream</a>.” The CD box was in excellent condition, and the printed materials were in great shape. The album had songs like “Cherub Rock” and “Today,” which were a reminder of the band’s impact on the alternative rock scene in the early 90s.</p>

<p>The seventh album was from the American grunge band Alice in Chains, and it was their third studio album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Alice-In-Chains/Alice-In-Chains/album-v2151b6f">Alice in Chains</a>.” The CD box was slightly damaged, but the printed materials were still in good shape. The album had songs like “Grind” and “Heaven Beside You,” which showcased the band’s unique sound and songwriting skills.</p>

<p>The eighth album was from the American rapper Nas, and it was his second studio album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Nas/It-Was-Written/album-v211362a">It Was Written</a>.” The CD box was in excellent condition, and the printed materials were in great shape. The album had hits like “The Message” and “If I Ruled the World (Imagine That),” which showcased Nas’ lyrical prowess and storytelling abilities.</p>

<p>The ninth album was from the American rock band Red Hot Chili Peppers, and it was their sixth studio album, “<a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Red-Hot-Chili-Peppers/One-Hot-Minute/album-v212b536">One Hot Minute</a>.” The CD box was in good condition, and the printed materials were intact. The album had songs like “Aeroplane” and “My Friends,” which were a testament to the band’s unique sound and style.</p>

<p>The tenth and final album was <a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Radiohead/Amnesiac/album-v212e6ee">Amnesiac</a> from the British rock band Radiohead.</p>

<p>I couldn’t wait to get started on this project, so I grabbed my laptop and started inserting the CDs one by one. As each CD was ripped, I carefully inspected the album art, liner notes, and lyrics. Some of the albums had extensive liner notes, with detailed information about the recording process and the musicians involved. Others had beautiful artwork and photos of the band members.</p>

<p>One of the albums I found was <a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Pink-Floyd/Dark-Side-Of-The-Moon/album-v21381c0">Dark Side of the Moon</a> by Pink Floyd. The CD was in good condition, with no scratches or visible signs of wear. The album art was stunning, with the iconic prism on the cover and the circular rainbow on the back. The liner notes included lyrics, credits, and a list of equipment used in the recording. I couldn’t wait to listen to this album again and hear the songs in high-quality mp3 format.</p>

<p>Another album I found was “Led Zeppelin IV.” The CD was in good condition, but the album art was a bit worn and faded. The liner notes were extensive, with detailed information about the recording process and the meanings behind the songs. I was especially excited to listen to “Stairway to Heaven” again, as it had been years since I had heard it.</p>

<p>As I worked my way through the CDs, I found myself getting lost in the music and the memories it brought back. Some of the albums were from my childhood, and listening to them again was like traveling back in time. Others were albums I had discovered later in life, and hearing them again reminded me of the moments when I first heard them.</p>

<p>In addition to ripping the CDs, I also did some research on each album and read some reviews. It was fascinating to learn more about the history and context of each album, and to see how they were received by critics and fans alike. I discovered that some of the albums I had found were considered classics, while others were more obscure but still beloved by fans.</p>

<p>One album that caught my attention was <a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Megadeth/Rust-In-Peace/album-v218c2be">Rust in Peace</a> by Megadeth. This album was released in 1990 and is considered a classic of the thrash metal genre. The CD was in good condition, with no visible scratches or wear. The album art was striking, with a black and white photo of the band and a colorful background. The liner notes included lyrics and credits, as well as a message from the band thanking their fans for their support.</p>

<p>Another album that stood out was <a href="https://www.tagtuner.com/music/albums/Jeff-Buckley/Grace/album-v24ff29">Grace</a> by Jeff Buckley. This album was released in 1994 and is considered a masterpiece of alternative rock. The CD was in good condition, with no visible scratches or wear. The album art was simple but beautiful, with a black and white photo of Jeff Buckley on the cover. The liner notes included lyrics and credits, as well as a tribute to Jeff Buckley, who tragically died in 1997.</p>

<p>As I finished ripping the last CD, I felt a sense of satisfaction and nostalgia. It had been an amazing experience to rediscover these albums and hear them again in high-quality mp3 format. I couldn’t wait to start listening to them and sharing them with my friends and family.</p>

<p>Finding these 10 rare old CDs and ripping them to mp3s was a wonderful experience that reminded me of the power of music to bring back memories and emotions. It was also a great opportunity to learn more about these albums and appreciate them in a new way. I highly recommend digging through your own collection of CDs and rediscovering some of your favorite albums. Who knows what memories and emotions they might bring back?</p>]]></content><author><name>John</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="database" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reliving my musical memories through digitization]]></summary></entry></feed>